ABID JAN

jan.abid1390@gmail.com +1 437 234 6746 London, ON, Canada Environmental Scientist, MS LEED Green Associate, USGBC

Profile

A conscientious, reliable and hardworking professional, pays attention to details, aware of work ethics, with excellent interpersonal and time management skills. Experience of more than 6 years in diversified fields of Sustainability and Environmental Services. Often being recognized as a self-motivated and ambitious professional who is eager to learn and take up new challenges.

Work Experience

Site Manager- UPI Energy (Gas Station)

Global West Realty

April 2019 to date

London, ON Canada

Responsibilities

- Oversee daily & weekly activities including purchasing and inventory duties;
- Managing daily sales activities, answering phone, serve customers and resolve related issues;
- Handling all sales transactions and preparing sales reports daily;
- Managing the back office, generating and sending daily reports to head office;
- Responsible for receiving and checking the accuracy and inspection of all deliveries;
- Maintaining the gas station in good condition;
- Monitoring and controlling internal/external safety issues of gas station; and
- Adjusting fuel prices on daily basis and ordering gas as needed.

Operations Manager

Nov 2016 to Feb 2019

Green Crescent Environmental Engineering Consultants

Abu Dhabi, UAE

GCEEC is an engineering consultancy for Environmental Compliance that offers inspection, testing, investigation and advice to customers through a range of technical expertise and accredited services.

Responsibilities

- Technical Review of Environmental Studies including EPA, PER, EIA, CEMP, WRR, EMP, EAP and other relevant studies;
- Coordination in Sustainability projects including Estidama, LEED, Al-Safat and other relevant studies including Energy Modeling and Commissioning;
- Reaching out to potential clients for need assessment in relevance to the scope of GCEEC;
- Supporting the Business Development team in proposal preparation and providing any technical support when required;
- Technical coordination with clients for the preparation and development of environmental and health and safety studies;
- Reviewing environmental monitoring reports as per the local and federal guidelines;
- Providing Technical support to the group when and where required.

Assistant Director-International Affairs

Feb 2015 to Nov 2016

COMSATS Headquarters

Islamabad, Pakistan

Commission on Science and Technology for Sustainable Development in the South (COMSATS) is an intergovernmental organizing having 24 member countries mandated to promote science and technology through International Thematic Research Groups (ITRGs).

Responsibilities

- Assisting the Executive Director COMSATS in International Affairs;
- Planning and Monitoring of various international projects of COMSATS Headquarters;
- Coordinating research activities with various scientific institutions in the member countries;
- Liaising with international organizations (including UNESCO, ISESCO, TWAS, and SESRIC) & diplomatic community for collaboration and joint efforts to help developing countries;
- Organizing national and international events for sensitizing the developing countries for science-led development;
- Editorial Support Team to COMSATS' International Scientific Journal and Bi-Monthly News Letter for Technical Evaluation and value addition of scientific research papers;
- Organized and coordinated "International Symposium on Light and Life, October 2015", to commemorate the UNESCO International Year of Light and Light-based Technologies;
- Organized and steered a Conference on Climate Change titled "UNFCCC, Kyoto Protocol and Beyond" as part of the COMSATS' Science Diplomacy Programme;
- Conducted "International Conference and Exhibition on Renewable Energy Technologies", as one of the main organizer.

Executive Officer- Environment

Aug 2014 to Feb 2015

SGS Pakistan

Islamabad, Pakistan

SGS is a multinational company headquartered in Geneva, Switzerland which provides inspection, verification, testing and certification services. It has more than 90,000 employees and operates over 2,000 offices and laboratories worldwide.

Responsibilities

- Performing a number of tasks related to Business Development of environmental services;
- Preparing proposals for clients according to their needs and requirements;
- Coordinating between clients and technical team for performing different activities related to environmental services;
- Providing support in field visits for carrying out environmental studies including EIA and IEE;
- Carried out Initial Environmental Examination Studies for Drilling of Tolanj East-1 and Tolanj South-1
 Wells for MOL Pakistan;
- Performed Indoor Air Quality Monitoring for OGDCL House and Chinese Embassy in Pakistan

Environmental Officer

Jan 2012 to Jun 2014

MCT Engineers

Islamabad, Pakistan

Management Consultancy and Training (MCT) Engineers is an Islamabad based engineering company involved mostly in providing design and construction consultancy services related to construction of roads and small dams.

Responsibilities

- Prepare, review, and update environmental reports;
- Provide technical support for environmental projects, including monitoring and testing;
- Provide administrative support to projects by collecting data, providing project documentation, training staff and performing other general administrative duties;
- Prepare proposals for Environmental Studies;
- Provide support in preparing EIA and IEE studies;
- Provide assistance in the Environmental aspects of Civil Engineering projects.

Miscellaneous Projects

- Worked as Coordinator in "Disaster Risk Insurance Framework in Pakistan", a project of Munich Climate
 Insurance Initiative (MCII) in collaboration with LEAD Pakistan in March 2014;
- Worked as Research Assistant with CDKN (Climate and Development Knowledge Network) in writing an Occasional paper titled, "Assessing the Risk of Loss and Damage due to Climate Change in Pakistan" in January-February 2014;
- Organized and Managed a national workshop, "National Consultation on Home Based Workers in Pakistan" as VR Member on behalf of ILO and UN-WOMEN;
- Experience of working with Vision21 (Non-Profit Organization) on a project "Clean Drinking Water Project" in flood affected areas from June to August 2011;
- 2 months internship in PEPAC (Pakistan Environmental Planning and Architectural Consultants) in July-August 2010.

Education

2012-2014 MS in Environmental Sciences, Bahria University, Pakistan

Analysis of Hydro-meteorological Parameters by Trend Detections and Correlations Using a Range of Statistical Techniques

2008-2012 BS in Environmental Sciences, Bahria University, Pakistan

Assessment of Socio-Psychological Impacts and Risk Calculation of Post-Flood Environmental Conditions- A Case Study

Certificates and Memberships

- LEED Green Associate, US Green Building Council
- IELTS Overall Band Score of 8.0
- Certificate of Participation in Training on Business Development Skills
- Certificate of capacity building training about Sexual and Reproductive Health and Rights
- Certificate on Games Management System
- Certificate of Appreciation for volunteering in 2010 Special Olympics
- Member of World Wide Fund for Nature (WWF)
- Member of Pakistan Environmentalists Association (PAE)